<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:dc='http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/'>
<channel>
<title>Grimgrains</title>
<link>https://grimgrains.com/</link>
<description>Grimgrains — a plantbased cooking blog</description>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0900</lastBuildDate>
<image>
  <url>https://grimgrains.com/media/services/rss.jpg</url>
  <title>Grimgrains — a plantbased cooking blog</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/</link>
</image>
<item>
  <title>chunky apple jam</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/chunky_apple_jam.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>chunky_apple_jam</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/chunky_apple_jam.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Every fall we volunteer with a <a href='https://lifecyclesproject.ca/' target='_blank'>local organization</a> to pick apples on private property that would normally go to waste. This year we got a lot of fruit so we decided to process some. We are not huge fans of compote, but we do like chunky-style jams.</p><p><b>Apples</b></p><p>We can't say for certain what kind of apple we picked, they looked like spartans or fujis, either way they are sweet and crisp and lend well to jams.</p><p><b>Botulism?</b> In the word of <a href='https://www.splendidtable.org/story/2013/08/02/in-jams-and-jellies-acidity-is-the-key-to-avoiding-botulism' target='_blank'>Kevin West</a>, acidity is the enemy of botulism. Foods that have a pH below 4.6, high-acid foods like apples, blueberries, strawberries (and many more) are completely safe, they have sufficient natural acidity to safeguard us against the risk of botulism. Despite this, it is still necessary to process the clean jars after filling them with jam.</p><p><b>Jam doneness</b><br><p> Apples normally have enough natural pectin to gel. Is my jam ready to take off the heat? There are three methods:</p><p><b>Temperature Test:</b> Take the temperature of the jelly with a candy or jelly thermometer. When done, the temperature of the jelly should be 100°C if you are at sea level. NOTE: For each 305 m of altitude above sea level, subtract 2 degrees. For instance, at 305 m of altitude, the jelly is done at 100°C; at 610 m, 102°C, etc<p><b>Spoon or Sheet Test</b>. Dip a cool metal spoon into the boiling jelly mixture and lift the spoon out of the steam so the syrup runs off the side. When the mixture first starts to boil, the drops will be light and syrupy. As the syrup continues to boil, the drops will become heavier and will drop off the spoon two at a time. When the two drops form together and sheet off the spoon, the jellying point has been reached.</p><p><b>Refrigerator/Freezer Test</b>. Pour a small amount of boiling jelly on a plate, and put it in the freezing compartment of a refrigerator for a few minutes. If the mixture gels, it should be done. During this test, the rest of the jelly mixture should be removed from the heat <a href='https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_07/jelly_point.html' target='_blank'>[ref]</a>.</p><p><b>Sugar.</b> Adding too little sugar may cause the jam to ferment. In this recipe, we added demerara sugar (it's what we had on hand) so this why the jam is dark. We like it because it has plenty of molasses in it, lending the jam a deep and pleasant toffee-esque flavor. Feel free to use other varieties of sugar, especially if you prefer a lighter-colored jam, or if you don't like the flavor of molasses.</p><p><b>Recommended Process Time</b></p><p>When processing jars in a boiler canner, the time varies depending on the altitude where you live. For this recipe (hot pack) the recommended time for those living from  0 - 305 m (0 - 1,000 ft) is 10 minutes, but the <a href='https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_07/apple_preserves.html' target='_blank'>National Center for Food Preservation</a> recommends 5 minutes, I do the longer time to avoid having to pre-boil the jars. For 305 m - 1829 m (1,001 - 6,000 ft) the time is 10 minutes, and 15 minutes for anyone above 1829 m (6,000 ft).</p><p><b>Sterilizing Empty Jars</b></p><p>It is unnecessary to presterilize jars for fruits, tomatoes, and pickled or fermented foods that will be processed 10 minutes or longer in a boiling-water canner.</div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/chunky_apple_jam.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>quick flat bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_flat_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>quick_flat_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/quick_flat_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A quick no-yeast flat bread recipe, ideal when you want bread but don't want to wait. The flat bread is ready in under 45 minutes (includes resting time), and it's possible to prepare under 15 minutes—we do this a lot—if necessary (without the resting time).</p><p>Allowing the dough to relax after kneading makes it easier to work with, but if you skip that step it's still possible to roll it out, it'll just be a bit harder to do.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions:</b></p><p><b>Flour:</b> Switching whole wheat flour for spelt, or all-purpose won't affect the dough.</p><p><b>Fat:</b> Fat is necessary in this recipe, it helps to create a smooth, rich and pliable dough. Using other types of oil, like canola or sunflower oil, is fine. It's possible to use vegan butter, but it's important to soften and mix it in with other liquids first. If using vegan butter, measure out 50 g.</p><p><b>Liquid:</b> For an even richer, and even MORE pliable dough, substitute water for plant milk. I recommend using soy, as it is richer than rice or oat milk. On the boat, we tend not to use milk because we rarely keep any (lacking a fridge).</p><p><b>Add-ins:</b> We sometimes like to add seeds, like sesame, flax or sunflower, to my breads. Add the seeds after adding water, folding them into the dough.</p><p><b>Sourdough discard:</b> to make this recipe with <a href='sourdough_starter.html'>sourdough discard</a>, measure 190 g (1 1/4 cups) of whole wheat flour and 113 g (1/2 cup) of the discard. You'll have to reduce the water, depending on the hydration level of your starter. We only added 130 ml of water instead of the full 180 ml. The sourdough won't provide much leavening or taste, this is just a way to add extra nutrition and to use discard.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_flat_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>roasted eggplant dip</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_eggplant_dip.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>roasted_eggplant_dip</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2009 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/roasted_eggplant_dip.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A simple roasted eggplant dip recipe. Roasting the garlic is optional, but it gives the dip a deeper, more complex flavor, while diminishing the pungency of the garlic.</p><p>This recipe is ideal when served with flat bread or raw vegetables, it's also good if served with <a href='crackers.html'>crackers</a>. Optionally, you can add roasted green peppers and other vegetables to further augment the flavor and nutrition of the dip.</p><p><b>Add-ins: </b> Add 20 g (~1/2 cup) of chopped parsley and/or 2 diced tomatoes for extra texture and flavor. For a more complex (and sweet) taste, add 45 ml (~3 tbsp) of pomegranate molasses. You can also use grape molasses.</p><p><b>Garlic: </b> The garlic doesn't need to be roasted, you can use it fresh. If you do this, you will have to use ~4-5 cloves instead of the whole head. Use a mortar and pestle to crush the peeled garlic into a paste before adding it to the rest of the ingredients.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_eggplant_dip.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>anise bread with sweet pear sauce</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/anise_bread_with_sweet_pear_sauce.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>anise_bread_with_sweet_pear_sauce</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/anise_bread_with_sweet_pear_sauce.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Since getting those mini silicone pans, we've been making mini everything. This time, we made some anise sweet bread topped with a sauce, and loaded with caramelized pear chunks.</p><p>My bag of anise seeds has been sitting in my pantry, for way too long, begging for purpose. We are happy to report that the taste of anise pairs very well with pears.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/anise_bread_with_sweet_pear_sauce.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>arame soba</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/arame_soba.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>arame_soba</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/arame_soba.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We cook a lot of Japanese-style food, not just because we lived there for a few years, but because we appreciate the subtle flavors and aesthetics of Japanese cuisine.</p><p><b>Soba</b>: In this recipe we used pre-packaged buckwheat noodles (そば soba), but it is possible to prepare from scratch using a 1:0.5 mixture of buckwheat and whole wheat flour. Making juwari soba 十割そば (100% buckwheat noodles) is very difficult to master, and is best left to the patient and the experienced, qualities we do not yet possess.</p><p><b>Arame</b>: <a href='arame.html'>Arame</a> is a species of kelp of a dark brown color, it has a mild, semi-sweet flavor and a firm texture. Arame is reconstituted in about 5 minutes, and we like to add to many kinds of dishes. It is high in calcium, iodine, iron, magnesium and vitamin A. This recipe used to include <a href='dried_hijiki.html'>hijiki</a>, but we've since removed it because it contains potentially toxic quantities of inorganic arsenic. Japan is the only country that doesn't warn against its consumption. Arame seaweed doesn't share this toxicity, and is a good substitute in both texture and taste.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/arame_soba.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>balsamic banana ice cream</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/balsamic_banana_ice_cream.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>balsamic_banana_ice_cream</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/balsamic_banana_ice_cream.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Banana ice cream is a simple alternative to dairy or coconut based desserts. It's a no-fuss recipe that requires little preparation and waiting time.</p><p>Making it is easy, and only requires putting bananas in the freezer. While waiting for them to harden up, prepare your balsamic coulis. If you've ever boiled balsamic vinegar, you know that it can sting your eyes. Making a balsamic vinegar reduction makes it thick and syrupy, and works well as a topping. We like the contrast of the bananas and vinegar.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/balsamic_banana_ice_cream.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>black sesame brittle</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/black_sesame_brittle.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>black_sesame_brittle</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/black_sesame_brittle.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Sesame brittle looks impressive when served over desserts, like small pieces of black coral.</p><p>It's simple to make, but requires all of your attention. The sugar syrup becomes solid when cool, so all steps must be done quickly. These are no-bake, and are ready to eat almost instantly.</p><p>These are best served over desserts that aren't too sweet, the sweet of the sesame brittle can be a bit overpowering, we suggest serving it with fruit, or <a href='#kanten_powder.html'>kanten</a> (agar agar based desserts).</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/black_sesame_brittle.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>black sesame syrup</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/black_sesame_syrup.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>black_sesame_syrup</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/black_sesame_syrup.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We like making syrups, or juice reductions a lot. It's simple, and you can use it in many other recipes afterwards. Reductions that aren't sweetened with sugar are great as an add-on to sauces, or when used alone as a 'glaze'.</p><p>We used a technique by the cook <a href='https://discoginferno.wordpress.com/tag/sesame-seed-syrup' target='_blank'>Mike Case</a>, he made a white sesame syrup to use in cocktails. We liked not requiring a blender to make it, blending sesame seeds into a smooth liquid is tough, my immersion blender can't grind seeds finely. Boiling the seeds, and then straining them out is simple, and since you can re-use the seeds afterwards, there's no waste. Toasting the seeds beforehand helps to bring out the nutty flavor, so don't skip that step.</p><p>This syrup pairs well with ice cream, especially those with subtle flavors like coconut and vanilla. It's delicious on fruit ice cream too. To make fruit ice cream, slice fruit of choice thinly. Lay a sheet of parchment paper over a plate, and lay your fruit overtop (this will keep the fruit from sticking). Let them freeze for a few hours, then run them through an immersion blender. You can use almost any fruit to make it, but it works especially well for <a href='mango.html'>mango</a> and <a href='bananas.html'>bananas</a>.</p><p>You can use the left-over seeds to bake into desserts, or to add as an extra topping.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/black_sesame_syrup.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>breaded chickpea tofu fingers</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/breaded_chickpea_tofu_fingers.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>breaded_chickpea_tofu_fingers</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/breaded_chickpea_tofu_fingers.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Was in the mood for some baked veggie fingers, didn't have tofu, but what we did have was a jar full of chickpea flour. We prepared a batch of spicy, green scallion 'chickpea tofu' and coated it with breadcrumbs.</p><p>The lemon juice adds flavor to the crumbs, no need for eggs or flour.</p><p>We served these with sambal oelek, it's spicy but works well with the dish. We've been pairing this condiment with a lot of foods lately, we are sure these would also be good with a sweet mustard dip</p><p>Left-over breading will keep for weeks if stored in an airtight container.</p><p>If using besan(gram) flour, add 2 extra tablespoons of flour.</div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/breaded_chickpea_tofu_fingers.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>brownies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/brownies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>brownies</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/brownies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>To make great brownies, you need to pay a special attention to how you treat the eggs and sugar. These two ingredients need good whipping to add heft to the batter.</p><p>How do you know you've got the whipping right? If you lift your whisk after mixing, the eggs will dribble in thick ribbons which hold their shape on top of the batter for a few seconds. This is what bakers call the <b>ribbon stage</b>. This ability of eggs to swell is the basis of great pastries and desserts, for leavening they don't need baking powder or baking soda and instead rely on the air held in place by the whipped eggs.</p><p>These properties aren't unique to chicken eggs. It's possible to get good ribboning with both flax seeds and aquafaba (liquid from chickpeas), but aquafaba yields better results in baking.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p><b>Fat :</b> Use 90 ml of canola oil instead of vegan butter. To make your own vegan butter, look for the recipe in <b>The Homemade Vegan Pantry by Miyoko Schinner</b>. It's possible to use less fat, but you can only substitute half the amount of fat before it affects the texture. For example, you can use 45 ml (1/8th cup) of vegetable oil (canola, sunflower) with 60 g (45 ml) of pumpkin puree.</p><p><b>Chocolate : </b>Use <a href='unsweetened_cocoa_powder.html'>unsweetened cocoa powder</a> instead of bar chocolate, for every 30 g (1 oz) of chocolate add 15 g (3 tbsp) of cocoa powder plus 15 g (1 tbsp) of vegan butter.</p><p><b>Tip : </b>To prevent burning the bottom of your brownies, place the pan on a preheated cookie sheet. Brownie tips courtesy of <a href='http://www.kitchenproject.com/history/Brownies/BrownieTips.htm#Mixing' target='_blank'>the kitchen project</a><p>.</div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/brownies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>carrot kinpira onigirazu</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/carrot_kinpira_onigirazu.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>carrot_kinpira_onigirazu</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/carrot_kinpira_onigirazu.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>An onigirazu is a Japanese rice ball sandwich, or a 'lazy onigiri'.</p><p>The word onigiri (or nigiru) means to press into shape using your hands, while "razu" means the opposite. Free form onigiri. This is perfect for people who have a hard time making rice balls. Onigirazu has the same great taste, without the fear of imperfection.</p><p>This recipe is perfect when you don't have the right type of rice available for onigiri. You can use just about any type, we tested it out a few different kinds. The seaweed wrapping will keep it together, yhus eliminating the need for sticky rice.</p><p>We seasoned the rice with miso for added flavor, and filled it with carrot kinpira—'kinpira' means "sauteed" (usually with a mixture of mirin soy sauce and chili peppers.) It's a sweet and spicy dish that the Japanese serve in bentos.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/carrot_kinpira_onigirazu_2.jpg'/></p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/carrot_kinpira_onigirazu.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>corn pone</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/corn_pone.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>corn_pone</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/corn_pone.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Corn pone has been part of our diet since 2016, ever since our good friend Claudia from the sailboat Essencia made some for us.</p><p>Corn pone is a simple version of cornbread, it is heavy, crunchy and thick, rather than fluffy and light.</p><p>This recipe is versatile, we use whatever vegetables we have on hand for the topping. If we have kimchi, we put kimchi, but this recipe is also delicious with chipotle peppers in adobo sauce, or with the vegetables sautéed with dried chili pepper flakes. In the above photo, we added black olives because we had some.</p><p>Instead of making one big corn cake, you can divide it into 4, or 8 smaller cakes. It's possible to eat them as is, without a topping, with or without a dollop of vegan butter.</p><p><b>Oven version</b></p><p>To prepare corn pone in the oven, preheat oven to 190 °C (375 °F). Preheat cast iron skillet in oven, then spread mixture in skillet. Bake for 30 min, or until edges start to brown.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/corn_pone.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>quick cheese</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_cheese.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>quick_cheese</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/quick_cheese.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>This is a quick, nut-free cheese recipe, that you can add onto if you want different flavors. It's simple to prepare, and ready under a few hours.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>In this recipe we use <a href='kanten.html'>kanten</a>, which is similar to <a href='agar_agar.html'>agar agar</a> except that it's made from a different type of red algae (tengusa). You can swap it 1:1 in a recipe, although the resulting texture will not be the same. Adding agar agar will soften the texture.</p><p>In this recipe, it's possible to replace 240 ml of <a href='soy_milk.html'>soy milk</a> with 240 ml of water instead, this will result in a cheese that is less creamy and less filling. We like to add <a href='ground_turmeric.html'>turmeric</a> to make it yellow, but it's totally optional.</p><p>It is also possible to the omit sunflower seeds, using mostly plant milk will still give good results. We make it this way if we forget to soak sunflower seeds. Another option, is to use soft tofu.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_cheese.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>cheese and spinach ravioli</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/cheese_and_spinach_ravioli.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>cheese_and_spinach_ravioli</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/cheese_and_spinach_ravioli.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We have arrived in New Zealand, the land of plenty. All of the foods that we like and miss are here. Foods like nutritional yeast, miso and soba (to name a few).<p><p>With a fully re-stocked pantry, we started to make faux-cheese again, a recipe from <a href='http://www.veganricha.com/2014/08/almond-milk-pepper-jack-cheese-vegan-glutenfree-recipe.html' target='_blank'>Vegan Richa</a> that is simple to make and that we love. The recipe is for a cheese that can be cut into wedges, or that can be grated over pizza. I had an idea to use this recipe to make filling for ravioli, the difference being that we won't add any agar agar (a seaweed based powder that makes liquids gellify)</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/cheese_and_spinach_ravioli_1.jpg'/></p><p>Making the ravioli is easy, and requires laying out a thin sheet of dough, and adding bits of the spinach and cheese mix into separate small mounds across. Leaving enough space between each 'mound' is necessary, as another sheet of dough is laid overtop and that the space ensures that both sheets will stick together.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/cheese_and_spinach_ravioli.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Choco peanut blondies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/choco_peanut_blondies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>choco_peanut_blondies</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/choco_peanut_blondies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A recipe that's ideal when we have chickpea left-overs, which happens a lot when cooking from dry beans. Sometimes we'll prepare chickpeas for this recipe, and use the rest as part of another meal, something like a <a href='chickpea_salad_sandwich.html'>chickpea salad sandwich</a> or <a href='spicy_stirfry_chickpeas.html'>spicy stir-fried chickpeas</a>.</p><p>We re-use the cooking liquid from the chickpeas in the same recipe, it works as a binding and leavening agent. When whipped at high speeds, the chickpea cooking liquid (or <a href='aquafaba.html'>aquafaba</a>) triples in size, and acts as an egg replacer.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations</b></p><p>I don't recommend re-using the liquid from cans of chickpeas, as it's technically the soaking liquid which ought to be discarded. Substituting canned chickpeas from home-cooked beans is fine, but if you do this, discard the liquid and use either a <a href='flax_seed_eggs.html'>flax egg</a> or ground and soaked chia seeds. These two ingredients can help bind ingredients, but aren't effective when it comes to leavening.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>It's possible to omit the cocoa powder, or to use double the quantity of peanut butter to 135 g (1 cup) instead of adding chickpeas. If you decide not to use chickpeas, be sure to add an egg replacer (chia or flax egg, as suggested above).</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/choco_peanut_blondies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>basic black bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/basic_black_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>basic_black_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/basic_black_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>This bread is super light and fluffy and great for morning toast or sandwiches.</p><p>We've been reading up a lot about bread, we wanted to understand how the ingredients we add can affect the texture. We also read about the differences in temperature, to knead or not to knead etc. Truth is, every choice depends on the desired end result.</p><p>We wanted to make a sandwich bread with a light crumb, the kind that bounces back when touched. This recipe has more fat, which in turn makes it softer and fluffier. The choice of fat will affect the texture/taste of the bread.</p><p>There are many things you can do to help soften your bread, like brushing the outside with a oil or some other fat as soon as we take it out of the oven. Brushing fat on the outside softens the crust.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>It's possible to substitute nut milk for water, for a richer taste.<p><b>Burger buns:</b> Repeat steps 1 to 6 in the recipe below. Instead of forming into a 'cigar' shape at step 7,divide into 8 pieces and shape into a tight ball. Sprinkle baking sheet with some cornmeal and put buns on top. Cover and let rise for another 45 minutes in the warmed oven. Take buns out of oven, brush lightly with 15 ml (1 tbsp) of coconut oil (for browning) and put white sesame seeds on top. Bake uncovered for 20 minutes at 180 °C (350 °F). Let cool on a pile of towels or cooling rack.</p><p><b>Hot dog buns:</b> Repeat steps 1 to 6. Divide through into 15 pieces and shape into small cylinders (or general elongated hot dog shape). Sprinkle baking sheet with some cornmeal and put buns on top. Cover and let rise for another 45 minutes in the warmed oven. Take buns out of oven, brush lightly with coconut oil. Bake uncovered for 20 minutes< at 180 °C (350 °F). Let cool on a pile of towels or cooling rack.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/basic_black_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>basic toothpaste</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/basic_toothpaste.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>basic_toothpaste</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/basic_toothpaste.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>In the last couple of years, we've removed most pre-made cleaning and hygiene products from our lives. In fact, we don't use shampoo at all anymore. We make our own toilet cleaner, kitchen cleaner, and we also make our own toothpaste.</p><p>Chances are you already have all of the ingredients at home to make it. The recipe consists of <a href='baking_soda.html'>baking soda</a>, <a href='coconut_oil.html'>coconut oil</a> and <a href='peppermint_oil.html'>peppermint oil</a> (food grade).</p><p>You can also brush your teeth with a simple baking soda and water mix (mix 1 tsp of baking soda with a small amount of water). Baking soda's relatively low abrasivity is enough to remove accumulations on teeth, and it rinses clear leaving a lightly salty taste. It's important to dilute the baking soda, as too much can be damaging. For those who dislike brushing with a salty taste, adding peppermint oil helps to smooth down both the taste and texture, although this ingredient is for taste, and it <a href='https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4606594/' target='_blank'>isn't yet known</a> if is truly effective against oral diseases.</p><p>As for the use of coconut oil, it is thought <a href='https://www.healthline.com/health/homemade-toothpaste#recipes' target='_blank'>to reduce plaque</a> after continued use. A downside to using coconut oil, is that it becomes solid in cold climates, and it's necessary to melt it down before using it. We like to put the jar near a source of heat for 5 minutes or so. Another detail to consider, is that the oil may clog your drain in cold weather. We've noticed this on our boat, and so we spit in a glass and pour it overboard.</p><p>The ingredients in homemade toothpaste vary, some add bentonite clay and other essential oils, we opted for the simplest recipe possible. Homemade toothpaste is controversial, as recipes lack fluoride, an ingredient that reduces cavities and that addresses other oral health conditions, but we believe that toothpaste is only as good as your brushing (which should last for a min of 2 min). It is more important to brush your teeth thoroughly than to use toothpaste, especially after eating sweets. In all, we prefer to avoid packaging and make our own, it works for us and it might work for you too.</p><p><b class='head'>Abrasion properties of baking soda</b></p><p>Tooth enamel is the hardest substance in the body, but some brands of abrasive toothpaste can wear it down, exposing the dentin lying beneath. To help quantify the abrasivity of dentifrices, researchers established a standardized scale called <a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abrasion_(dental)#Relative_dentin_abrasivity' target='_blank'>Relative Dentin Abrasivity (RDA)</a>. This scale assigns toothpaste an abrasivity value, relative to a standard reference abrasive that is arbitrarily given an RDA value of 100. All dentifrices at or below 2.5 times the reference value, or 250 RDA, are considered safe and effective [1]. In fact, clinical evidence supports that lifetime use of proper brushing technique with a toothbrush and toothpaste at an RDA of 250 or less produces limited wear to dentin and virtually no wear to enamel [2]. Sodium bicarbonate (baking soda) has a <a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohs_scale_of_mineral_hardness' target='_blank'>Mohs hardness</a> value of 2.5 and an RDA value of 7.</p><p><b class='head'>Sources</b></p><p>[1] St John S, White DJ. History of the Development of Abrasivity Limits for Dentifrices. J Clin Dent 2015;26(2):50-4.</p><p>[2] Hunter ML, Addy M, Pickles MJ, Joiner A. The Role of Toothpastes and Toothbrushes in the Aetiology of Tooth Wear. Int Dent J 2002;52:399-405.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/basic_toothpaste.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>beer bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/beer_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>beer_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/beer_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>The idea of making beer bread came from a book written by Lin Pardey called "The Care and Feeding of the Offshore Crew". In this book, Lin talks about cooking at sea, and has an entire chapter dedicated to baking onboard. In this chapter, the author talks about the many ways to make fresh bread while sailing, including a quickbread recipe that uses 3 basic ingredients: flour, sugar and beer.</p><p>Beer bread you say? Right up our alley. The next day we gave it a try, the result was fantastic.</p><p>The amazing thing about beer bread is that using different beer, will change the flavor and color of the bread. We tried baking with an IPA (21st amendment), a Hefeweizen (Sunriver brewing co) and a brown ale (Hobgoblin).</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>If you have self-rising flour, you can omit the baking powder and salt. Also, you can omit the leavening agent if you have a craft beer that has live yeast sediment at the bottom of the bottle, although most manufacturers filter it out. </p><p>To make a sandwich bread-style loaf, add a tbsp of fat (vegan butter or olive oil).</p><p>We made a video of the beer bread-making process, check it out <a href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ppASJRVcXmM' target='_blank'>here</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/beer_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>breadfruit gnocchi</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/breadfruit_gnocchi.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>breadfruit_gnocchi</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/breadfruit_gnocchi.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We are about to leave Tonga, the tropics and the land of bountiful <a href='breadfruit.html'>breadfruit</a>. This versatile fruit can be cooked into fries, eaten with <a href='coconut_milk.html'>coconut milk</a>, made into chips, or like this recipe suggests, it makes good gnocchi.</p><p>Breadfruit has a taste and texture that resembles that of <a href='potato.html'>potato</a>, and so it makes sense that it too can be made into gnocchi. The flesh of the fruit can be kneaded with ease, especially if the fruit is very ripe. I have tried to knead it when half-ripe, it works too, but requires added moisture and more kneading, not to mention that it doesn't have as much flavor. Ripe breadfruit develops a sweet taste. It can be difficult to catch it at the right moment, like avocados they have a tendency to overripen overnight. Because we like it so much, we've bought many and have had time to better tell when it can be eaten. The outside becomes soft to the touch, but only just.</p><p>We serve these with a light sauce, to better taste the gnocchi. A sauce that we enjoy, is minced garlic and chili peppers cooked in olive oil. The sauce is poured overtop and sprinkled with bits of shredded nori.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/breadfruit_gnocchi.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>breadfruit pasta</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/breadfruit_pasta.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>breadfruit_pasta</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/breadfruit_pasta.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Yes, another <a href='breadfruit.html'>breadfruit</a> recipe! This fruit is one of the most versatile ingredients we've ever cooked with, it's cheap and pairs well with just about anything. When we returned to the south pacific last June, you can be sure that the first thing we went looking for at the market was this lovely green wonder. It's become a staple for us, a treat and food we are excited to cook and eat.</p><p>While in a grocery store in Fiji, we spotted breadfruit flour! A company called <b><a href='http://friendfiji.com' target='_blank'>Friend's Fiji style</a></b> sells it in bags of 300g. It's a good alternative if the fresh kind can't be found. It's something we'll stock up on when we leave, so we continue to have breadfruit in our diet (in some form).</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/breadfruit_pasta_1.jpg'/></p><p>Making pasta from scratch requires your hands, a knife and a rolling pin (or bottle, whatever works). Making pasta by hand that is even and thin is a challenge, it's easier to opt for thicker 'udon-style' noodles. Expert soba chefs in Japan can cut noodles thinly, but this requires experienced hands. We have a good blade, but lack the patience as well as the desire to cut even noodles. We're very okay with imperfect noodles.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/breadfruit_pasta_2.jpg'/></p><p><b>Tricks for cutting pasta evenly:</b> Roll the flattened piece of dough and cutting it cross-wise is the key, the details on how to do this are in the recipe instructions below.</p><p>If you come to Fiji and like to make pasta from scratch, try and find some breadfruit flour. That same company also produces cassava flour.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/breadfruit_pasta_3.jpg'/></p><p>We like to eat breadfruit pasta with garlic, chilis and bitter melon, sauteed in olive oil with some shredded nori on top- simple, and tasty. Alternatively, to make regular pasta, just sub the breadfruit flour for 85 g of <a href='whole_wheat_flour.html'>whole wheat flour</a> or 75 g <a href='spelt_flour.html'>spelt flour</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/breadfruit_pasta.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>buckwheat dumplings</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/buckwheat_dumplings.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>buckwheat_dumplings</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/buckwheat_dumplings.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A recipe for the March 2021 Merveilles Cooking Jam.</p><p>Our default buckwheat recipes include <a href='buckwheat_tea.html'>Buckwheat Tea</a> and <a href='arame_soba.html'>Soba</a>. We like making soba, but it is a long, and messy process. Buckwheat is difficult to work with, especially if the aim is to make 100% soba (most are cut with wheat flour). So this recipe is a way to eat more buckwheat in our diet without defaulting to soba.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p><b>Buckwheat:</b> It is possible to use pre-ground flour, I just like to grind my own because it keeps longer as groats. If buying flour, you'll notice a darker and lighter variety, using either is fine. The darker variety has the hull mixed in, and the lighter version doesn't. Hulled buckwheat has more nutrients.</p><p><b>Tomato:</b> tomato paste is a concentrate, it is useful on a boat as it helps save space (instead of carrying larger cans). When using tomato paste, use it with equal parts water. If using whole tomatoes from a can, be sure to crush the tomatoes to help release its juices, and don't add extra water. The cooking time might be longer to help reduce and thicken the liquid. Using fresh tomatoes is another obvious option. Cut, and crush them with a fork in the pan when cooking.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/buckwheat_dumplings.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>buckwheat tea</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/buckwheat_tea.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>buckwheat_tea</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/buckwheat_tea.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A friend from Japan gave us some soba cha <b>そば茶</b> last month, it's something we've had before but that we never thought of making ourselves. It's a type of tea that is served in some soba shops, as a companion drink to buckwheat noodles. It has a subtle nutty flavor, and is perfect to drink after dinner, or later at night as it doesn't have any caffeine.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/buckwheat_tea_1.jpg'></p><p> We roast the groats as we need them, but it's possible to prepare a larger batch ahead of time. The roasted buckwheat groats will store for a few months if kept in a cool and dry place. </p><p><b>Roasting a larger batch:</b> When roasting a larger batch, use a larger pan so that the groats don't sit atop of each other. The groats must be in a single layer so they can cook evenly.</p><p> <b>Re-using the softened groats:</b> It's possible to re-use the softened groats by pouring more water onto them, although the flavor will not be as strong. If you like to minimize food waste, it's possible to incorporate the soft groats in other meals for bulk. For example, you can mix it into rice, cookies, breads etc.</p><p> <b>Cooking groats using oven:</b> You can roast your buckwheat groats in your oven. Roast them at 180 °C (350 °F) for 50 minutes, while stirring on occasion.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/buckwheat_tea.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>chickpea salad sandwich</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/chickpea_salad_sandwich.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>chickpea_salad_sandwich</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/chickpea_salad_sandwich.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We ordered ingredients from BC Kelp, a company in northern Canada that grows their own seaweed. A lot of the food we make these days has either nori, wakame, bull kelp or bladderwack whole tips in it.</p><p>We'd like to see more people cooking with sea vegetables. You can snack on dried seaweed, or add it to soups and salads. The powdered version we're using in this recipe adds a lot of umami and color to meals.</p><p>You can order your own bull kelp powder from the <a href='http://www.bckelp.com/index.html' target='_blank'>BC Kelp website</a>, they have a wide range of quality seaweed to choose from.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations</b></p><p>Adding a bay leaf, a bit of onion or a clove or two of garlic to the cooking water add a subtle seasoning to the chickpeas and boost flavor.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>If you don't have access to <a href='bull_kelp_powder.html'>bull kelp powder</a>, you can use 5 ml capers or dulse flakes. They will impart a delicious, briny, no-tuna taste.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/chickpea_salad_sandwich.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>chocolate chip cookies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/chocolate_chip_cookies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>chocolate_chip_cookies</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/chocolate_chip_cookies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We've been making chocolate chips cookies for a while, but never thought it worthy of a recipe because there are so many online already. In the interest of posting absolute basic recipes though, we felt it deserved to be written down, especially because cookie chemistry is difficult. Slight differences in moisture content, altitude, fat content and sugar content can alter the look and texture of a cookie. There are reasons for the quantities and choice of each ingredient, all interact with each other to give cookies their sweet and soft texture.</p><p>This recipe is a good base. Substitutions are possible, but changing ingredients—depending on the ingredient—can mess up your recipe. In our suggestions we give examples of good substitutions, and how to modify the recipe to get a good result.<b class='head'>Substitutions</b> <b>Flour:</b> If you choose to use spelt flour, a more nutritious alternative, add 5 ml (5 ml) of baking powder to help it rise.</p><p><b>Fat:</b> The fat in cookies is a big part of their structure. We've added vegan butter as it behaves like actual butter, it helps create baked goods that are more tender by shortening gluten strands. When fat coats flour, it slows down the process of gluten formation creating a more tender product <a href='https://bakerbettie.com/function-of-butter-in-baking/#The_Function_of_Butter_in_Baking'>ref</a>. To make your own vegan butter, look for the recipe in <b>The Homemade Vegan Pantry by Miyoko Schinner</b>.</p><p><b>Sugar:</b> Sugar is important in cookies, it helps with the flavor, color and texture. The oven temperature causes the sugar to react with the proteins, this is what gives baked goods their brown color. Natural brown sugar is important in this recipe, as it adds moisture to the dough. If you use 100% granulated white sugar the cookie won't spread as well, not unless you add more moisture.</p><p><b>Add-ins:</b> If you have a sensitivity to caffeine use <a href='carob_chips.html'>carob chips</a> instead of chocolate chips. Switching to carob won't affect the cookies. <b class='head'>Troubleshooting</b>"I followed the recipe, but my cookies don't look the same as yours!" The quirkiness of different ovens makes it difficult to give accurate cooking times. Having a thermometer in your oven is the best way to read the temperature accurately.</p><p><b>Help! Cookie spreading too much!</b> If your cookie is spreading too much, you may have added too much sugar. Sugar is hygroscopic, it absorbs liquid but once it bakes it releases that and if there's too much, then it keeps spreading. Oven temperature is another factor. The hotter the oven, the more quickly the fat melts before the cookies have time to set. Depending on your oven, you may need to bake cookies longer but at a lower temperature.</p><p><b>Help! Cookie not spreading!</b> One of the most common reasons why cookies don't spread is because there's too much flour in the dough. Try using less, and consider increasing the commercial brown sugar by a few tablespoons. This will add slightly more moisture and help the cookies spread. Be sure you're also using room temperature ingredients, especially butter, to promote the best spread and texture.</p><p>Read more about <a href='https://www.kingarthurflour.com/blog/2016/03/14/cookie-chemistry-2'>cookie chemistry</a>. Recipe inspired from <a href='https://www.kingarthurflour.com/recipes/chocolate-chip-cookies-recipe'>this one</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/chocolate_chip_cookies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>coffee jelly</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/coffee_jelly.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>coffee_jelly</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/coffee_jelly.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Coffee jelly is a popular dessert and drink (you could say) that is served in coffee shops in Japan. It is very simple to make, it doesn't require refrigeration to become jelly and it is delicious!</p><p>The key ingredient in this recipe is kanten, or agar agar, a gelling agent that is algae based and that is widely available in asia. It is available in powder form, and also in sheets. Sheets can be melted in a liquid the same way as the powder form. Agar agar has no calories, and imparts no flavor.</p><p>You can use instant coffee as well for this recipe, using 30 ml of instant coffee per cup.</p><p>On Pino, we sometimes make the mix without a sweetener, and pour a spoonful on top afterwards.</p><p><b class='head'>Quick soy pudding</b></p><p>You can eat the coffee jelly as is, or you can add the cubes in another recipe like a coconut or soy milk pudding. It can also be used as a garnish for other desserts.</p><p>Also, we sometimes make a quick 'soy pudding' by heating some soy milk in a pan with some arrowroot starch. The mixture will thicken, it becomes pudding-like and is delicious over coffee jelly.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/coffee_jelly.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>corn dumplings</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/corn_dumplings.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>corn_dumplings</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/corn_dumplings.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We found an old vegetarian cookbook in a book-sharing shelf. We must have spent an hour reading through it, the recipes were fantastic, the title read "The Farm Vegetarian Cookbook". The cookbook had an entire section dedicated to cooking with corn. It's in there that we found a recipe for masa dumplings.</p><p>Masa is corn that is simmered and ground into a paste and is the base for many recipes. You can make Mexican-style tortillas with it, that, or you can use it to make dumplings! We don't have access to fresh corn, nor do we have the space or the time to make my own masa, but we used <a href='cornmeal.html'>corn meal</a> instead and it worked! The only difference is that you need to add boiling water so you can roll the mixture into balls. If you were to use masa, you wouldn't need the added moisture.</p><p>The texture of the dumplings is fun and chewy. The outside is soft, but the inside is like that of dense cornbread.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations:</b></p><p>We enjoy eating it with tomato sauce or with a spicy apricot sauce. Instead of apricot jam, you can add apricot juice to the mix (orange will taste wonderful too). We added jam because I didn't have any juice on the boat, and besides, it works well in this recipe.</p><p>Adding extra spices, like cumin, chili flakes and turmeric will add a nice flavor to the dumpling mix.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/corn_dumplings.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>crackers</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/crackers.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>crackers</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/crackers.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Making crackers is simple. There are no downsides to knowing, and in a bind it's a useful skill. What's great about a basic recipe is that you can swap ingredients with little consequence (most times) and you can add to it to suit your needs and cravings.</p><p>We love to eat crackers as snacks, usually between breakfast and lunch, a cracker with some peanut butter to quiet our stomachs. We rely on crackers a lot during long passages at sea.</p><p>You can make these crackers without extras with just the 'cracker' portion of the recipe. They're just as delicious that way, but you can add seeds and spices for added flavor and nutrition. We like to add seeds to ours, like <a href='pumpkin_seeds.html'>pumpkin seeds</a>, <a href='flax_seeds.html'>flax seeds</a>, <a href='sesame_seeds.html'>sesame seeds</a>, or <a href='sunflower_seeds.html'>sunflower seeds</a>. We recommend adding <a href='black_pepper.html'>black pepper</a>, or <a href='chili_pepper_flakes.html'>chili pepper flakes</a>, these are also delicious if you sprinkle some salt over the top of them.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions :</b></p><p><b>Oats : </b> Instead of oats processed into powder, you can use 20 g (1/4 cup) of <a href='chickpea_flour.html'>chickpea flour</a> or 30 g of <a href='buckwheat_flour.html'>buckwheat flour</a>. Sometimes we make crackers that use spelt flour.</p><p><b>Buckwheat groats reuse: </b> Whenever we brew a batch of <a href='buckwheat_tea.html'> buckwheat tea</a>, we end up with some wet groats which we use in this cracker recipe. The groats will add extra moisture to the recipe, so be careful when adding water, you'll need a lot less.</p><p><b>Oil :</b> You can use any kind of oil, but prioritize mid-neutral oils like olive (like in the recipe) or aromatic oils like sesame and chili oil. Adding sunflower oil or canola is fine, but since these crackers are very basic, adding an strongly-flavored oils will improve the taste. If you're adding plenty of spices, adding aromatic oils isn't as crucial.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/crackers.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Soy flour tofu</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/soy_flour_tofu.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>soy_flour_tofu</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/soy_flour_tofu.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Over the years, we've experimented with various ways of making tofu, our favourite recipe is made from milling, and then soaking, the ground soy beans for a short time. We prefer making our own soy flour with a grain mill. It's possible to buy pre-ground flour, but make sure it isn't de-fatted.</p><p>Tofu is cheap to make. In Canada, 400g of soy beans costs about 0.35$ in bulk and makes a brick of tofu, the store bought equivalent 400g brick is 3.65$.</p><img src='../media/recipes/soy_flour_tofu_4.jpg'/><p>Making tofu from the flour is faster, there is no need to pre-soak the whole beans overnight, it also makes it easier for us to extract more milk.</p><p><b>Nigari</b> is our preferred coagulant, as it imparts less flavor than lemon juice, vinegar or epsom salt.</p><p>We got the idea to make this kind of tofu from <b>The Farm Vegetarian Cookbook</b> by Louise Hagler, and found general tofu-making tips from <b>Cooking With Tofu</b> by Yoshiko Takeuchi.</p><img src='../media/recipes/soy_flour_tofu_1.jpg'/><p>Making tofu on a boat is great, we use the hand-rail to suspend the nylon bag when pressing the milk out of the soy pulp.</p><img src='../media/recipes/soy_flour_tofu_2.jpg'/><p>It is always exciting to see the tofu curds separate from the whey.</p><img src='../media/recipes/soy_flour_tofu_3.jpg'/><p>Making tofu in a bag only is a no-fuss option. You don't need a mold to make tofu. The tofu has little bumps on it because of the perforated surface we drained it on.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/soy_flour_tofu.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>fresh pesto pasta</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/fresh_pesto_pasta.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>fresh_pesto_pasta</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/fresh_pesto_pasta.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>The combination of carrots and zucchinis look beautiful on a plate. To complete the dish, we added some roasted pumpkin seeds, and topped it off with cherry tomatoes. For bulk, we added cavatappi pasta to this dish. Cavatappi pasta (or scoobi-doo) happens to be our favorite pasta cut (we're a sucker for shapes)</p><p>See how to roast your own <a href='roasted_pumpkin_seeds.html'>pumpkin seeds</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/fresh_pesto_pasta.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>halloween pumpkin cookies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/halloween_pumpkin_cookies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>halloween_pumpkin_cookies</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/halloween_pumpkin_cookies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Been a while since we've baked cookies. It being pumpkin season, the choice was obvious.</p><p>These are not very sweet, namely because of the addition of coconut sugar which has a subtle and more complex taste. Coconut sugar will make your cookies a darker shade of orange, almost brown, and we think it fits nicely with the toned-down color of the pumpkin seeds. If you want a bold orange color, use white cane sugar instead.</p><p><b>Left over chocolate:</b> This recipe makes more chocolate than is needed for the recipe. If you want to keep it for later, pour it in a chocolate mold or shallow container and put it in the freezer. It will become solid and you'll have delicious homemade chocolate on the side for later times! Once it's solid, pop it out of the mold and put it in a closed container. Keep it in the freezer until you're ready to eat it!</p><p>Pumpkin puree how-to: Remove seeds and stringy flesh from pumpkin. Cut the pumpkin into large chunks and place on a baking sheet. Preheat oven at 180 °C (350 ºF). Roast pumpkin for 45 minutes until pumpkin is soft and tender. Let cool. Remove skin, and process into a food processor or use a handstick blender. If pumpkin puree is too wet, strain liquid through cheese cloth, if too dry, add a bit of water. The puree keeps for 3 days in the fridge, and up to 3 months frozen.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/halloween_pumpkin_cookies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>veganaise</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/veganaise.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>veganaise</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/veganaise.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Making mayo is easy. This is a basic recipe that doesn't take long to prepare, and that requires few tools.</p><p>It's possible to add other spices and ingredients to augment the flavor, like smoked paprika, garlic or fresh herbs. This recipe lends well to substitutions:</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p><b>Oil :</b> It's possible to use other neutral oils like sunflower oil, but we wouldn't recommend using olive oil as it will impart too much flavor.</p><p><b>Traditional mayo :</b> This recipe uses less oil than the average mayo recipe. We used soft tofu to have a thicker mixture to avoid adding extra oil, for a richer veganaise you can use soy milk or other plant milks. To do this, mix your ingredients in the order listed in the recipe (switching the tofu for 250 ml or 1 cup plant milk), then pour 350 ml to 595 ml (1 1/2 to 2 1/2 cups) of oil in a slow, and steady stream with the blender running. The mayo will thicken after ~4-5 minutes of blending.</p><p><b>Mustard : </b>Instead of using <a href='dijon_mustard.html'>prepared mustard</a>, you can sub with 5 g (1 tsp) of mustard powder. If you have a spice grinder or a coffee grinder, you can grind your own mustard powder from whole mustard seeds. In this recipe, we used old style <a href='dijon_mustard.html'>dijon mustard</a> with mustard seeds, which explains the texture present in the veganaise. If you want to know how to make old-style dijon mustard, check out <a href='#mustard_from_seed.html'>my recipe</a>.</p><p><b>Sweetener : </b>If you prefer sweeter venagaise, add 5 g (1 tsp) of a sweetener.</p><p><b>Vinegar :</b> Substitute lemon for apple cider vinegar, using equal amounts.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/veganaise.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>hop ice cream</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/hop_ice_cream.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>hop_ice_cream</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/hop_ice_cream.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We like craft beer a lot. To help satisfy our evergrowing craving, we decided to try and make hop flavored ice cream.</p><p>This ice cream is definitely for people who love the smell and taste of hops (as well as cold summer dairy-free treats).</p><p>We weren't sure how to 'infuse' the hops into the ice cream base, we tried making hop tea by infusing it overnight in the fridge, but the taste wasn't strong enough. Felt we would get better results and better flavor if the hops were heated. The pouch method worked pretty well, the ice cream base was perfect! Full of delicious bitterness! We may try making a concentrate with the hops first to mix into the base next time.</p><p>The hops used in this recipe are an American variety called "Colombus". We got them from <a href='http://www.choppeabarrock.com' target='_blank'>La Choppe a Barrock</a> on Villeneuve and Coloniale in Montreal. Every time we make home brews, we pick up the ingredients there! You can buy a wide variety of hop buds there, you can even get the pellet kind.</p><p>It was our second time using an ice cream maker, we got it for free. It looks like a little red pail—super cute. The woman I got it from even had the manual! You can make ice cream without a machine, although having one helps with the churning process. It saves a lot of time and effort. If we hadn't gotten that ice cream maker for free, we don't think we'd have one now, but since it's here might as well use it!</p><p>If you too, are having too many beers these days, try and cook with hops instead. Same taste, different format!</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/hop_ice_cream.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>houjicha overnight oatmeal</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/houjicha_overnight_oatmeal.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>houjicha_overnight_oatmeal</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/houjicha_overnight_oatmeal.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Oats are great when combined with the nutty and earthy flavor of houjicha. If you're not familiar with houjicha, visit a tea shop and ask for it, it's a Japanese roasted tea that is often served with sweet and savoury dishes. It's a good low-caffeine alternative to most teas, and adds just the right amount of flavor to oatmeal without overpowering it.</p><p><b class='head'>Suggestions</b></p><p>If your nut milk is sweetened, you may not need an added sweetener. It's also possible to use a tea strainer instead of a cloth bag by putting the loose leaves in it, and letting it sit in a shallow pan. Just keep an eye on it to make sure it doesn't tip!</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/houjicha_overnight_oatmeal.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>red lentil stew</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/red_lentil_stew.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>red_lentil_stew</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/red_lentil_stew.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A recipe we've prepared several times on long ocean passages, it's a one-pot recipe that is very versatile, filling and quick to prepare.</p><p><b class='head'>How to serve</b></p><p>We sometimes just eat it as is, or serve it on top of pasta (as a sauce) or <a href='basmati_rice.html'>basmati rice</a>. We also like to serve it with <a href='quick_flat_bread.html'>flat bread</a>.</p><p>This dish is also delicious with <a href='chili_pepper_flakes'>chili pepper flakes</a>.</p><p>Another alternative is to serve it as a side dish, to omit the lentils, add more vegetables and to cook them with the same spices in a pan. </p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>The recipe works well with most vegetables, it's easy to adapt and won't affect the taste or cooking time of the dish. Take note that adding red cabbage instead of green will alter the colour of the dish. Cooking the lentils with water instead of vegetable broth is possible, the spices add enough flavor. I also sometimes add konbu dashi as a more neutral base.</p><p>For a more complex taste, add cardamom, fenugreek seeds and cinnamon.</p><p>Only use shelled lentils, as whole lentils take longer to cook and the vegetables will soften too much. An alternative is to use <a href='sprouting.html#garbanzo' target='_blank'>sprouted whole brown lentils</a>, they'll cook as quickly as red lentils and are more nutritious.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/red_lentil_stew.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>lentils with roasted beet sauce</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/lentils_with_roasted_beet_sauce.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>lentils_with_roasted_beet_sauce</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/lentils_with_roasted_beet_sauce.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>This recipe is especially good and filling with lentils, but it's also possible to serve it on other grains or even pasta. We used beluga lentils, because they hold their shape better than <a href='brown_lentils.html'>brown lentils</a>.</p><p>Beets make any dish beautiful, but it can stain your skin. Not to worry though, it doesn't stay, you'll just look like you've just killed something.</p><p>Fresh mint is key in this recipe, don't omit it. If you have a fresh supply at home, that is perfect, otherwise store-bought stalks are fine. You can keep store-bought stalks longer if you do these simple steps: first, tear off any wilted leaves, wash the mint gently, and then put the stalks in a glass with a bit of water and a bag over the top. Then, store it in a cool space.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/lentils_with_roasted_beet_sauce.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>mason jar bread pudding</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/mason_jar_bread_pudding.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>mason_jar_bread_pudding</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/mason_jar_bread_pudding.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Growing up bread pudding was Rekka's favorite dessert. Rekka's mom used bread crusts left over from christmas dinner (from making no-crust sandwiches) to make bread pudding. Rekka's mom cooks by feel, always has. She never writes anything down. Rekkas stood by her as she made it, taking notes of the approximate quantities and various steps.</p><p>Rekka's mom comes from a family of 7 girls, she grew up cooking for the family. When cooking for the family, she'd always prepare a basin-load of food. Her bread pudding recipe is no different. Rekka's dad has no trouble going through all of it.</p><p>We are good eaters, but there's no way we can eat that much dessert, so we reduced and reduced, until it fit a wide-mouth 1/4 l(1 cup) mason jar.</p><p>If ever you have some leftover crusts try and make this, it's easy, delicious and comforting, and scales well enough. A  Rekka's mom would say, 'do it by eye'.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/mason_jar_bread_pudding.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>mustard from seed</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/mustard_from_seed.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>mustard_from_seed</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/mustard_from_seed.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We always try our hardest to buy as few packaged foods as we can, and if we do buy pre-made goods we aim for glass, this too through isn't always possible.</p><p>We ran out of mustard the other day, and couldn't find any at the store that wasn't packaged in plastic. We decided then that it was better to make our own. It requires few ingredients, little time to prepare (25 min for prep, few days for soaking), and is inexpensive.</p><p>First, you need some mustard seeds. You can choose between yellow, brown and black seeds, the color affects the 'heat' of the mustard. A dark seed imparts more flavor than the lighter variety, and is what we used in this recipe. The seeds are then soaked in a mixture of water and <a href='apple_cider_vinegar.html'>apple cider vinegar</a>, although you can also use beer and white wine as a base. The water should be room temperature or cold, because using hot liquids denatures the enzymes that create the 'heat' in mustard.</p><p>We don't have <a href='tools.html'>tools</a> onboard that require electricity, so to grind and crush seeds and herbs we use a <b>heavy ceramic mortar and pestle</b>.</p><p>After the mustard is ground, it is stored in a glass jar at room temperature. Because of its antibacterial properties, mustard <b>does not require refrigeration</b>.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/mustard_from_seed_1.jpg'/></p><p>The best thing about making it yourself is that you can vary the quantities and base ingredients according to your personal preferences. If you don't like having a strong vinegar taste, you can lessen the amount of apple cider vinegar and add more water instead. You can also add spices and sweeteners. For traditional 'yellow mustard', all you need to do is add turmeric (for color) and a sweetener.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/mustard_from_seed.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>no knead bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/no_knead_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>no_knead_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/no_knead_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p><b>No knead bread</b> is the easiest kind of artisan-style bread you can make at home, it requires little effort and absolutely no kneading what-so-ever.</p><p>This forgiving recipe allows for substitutions and additions of ingredients without altering the final texture of the bread. If you bake a whole wheat loaf, you might want to add 5 g of <a href='gluten_flour.html'>gluten flour</a> to help it rise.</p><p>The bread can be left to rise overnight. I usually mix it at around 2100, and bake it early the next morning at 0800. Unlike a lot of bread recipes, there is no second rise, and you don't need to knead or monitor it at all, because the gluten develops on its own. It's a recipe that is very hard to fail at, and you'll get good bread every time!</p><p>We sometimes add spices to the dough, like <a href='chili_pepper_flakes.html'>chili</a> and <a href='garlic.html'>garlic</a>, or we make a more hearty bread by adding <a href='pumpkin_seeds.html'>pumpkin seeds</a> or <a href='sunflower_seeds.html'>sunflower seeds</a>. Experiment with it!</p><p><b>Baking without a dutch oven</b></p><p>If you don't have a cast-iron container with a lid, you can use a baking pan with foil. This is the method I use, because I lack a good lid. While the bread doesn't have a hard top crust, the result is still great (the bottom will be tougher than the top). Coat the bread pan with <i>15 ml (1 tbsp)</i> <a href='olive_oil.html'>olive oil</a>, and sprinkle the inside of the pan with some <a href='cornmeal.html'>cornmeal</a> (enough to cover it all in a thin coat). The cornmeal will keep the dough from sticking to the pan. Bread pans don't keep their temperature as well as cast-iron cookware, so the bread will stick due to lack of heat. Oiling the pan is necessary.</p><p><b>Sourdough version</b></p><p>To make sourdough no-knead bread, replace the commercial yeast with a little less than 170 g (3/4 cup) of healthy, well-fed <a href='sourdough_starter.html'>sourdough starter</a>. Give the dough an extra long rise and then transfer the proofed dough into a hot cast-iron pot with a lid.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/no_knead_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>okonomiyaki</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/okonomiyaki.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>okonomiyaki</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/okonomiyaki.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p><b>Okonomiyaki</b> (meaning, 'grilled as you like it') is a Japanese dish, similar to the American omelette, but the main difference is the variation of ingredients. Typical okonomiyaki are made with eggs, and often include meat or fish. Making it without meat is simple enough, but without eggs? Back when we lived in Tokyo, our experience in cooking with plants was limited, but now we've been doing it long enough that we can think of alternatives with ease.</p><p>The key ingredient? <a href='chickpea_flour.html'>Chickpea flour</a>. We make chickpea pancakes, and <a href='scrambled_chickpea_flour.html'>scrambled chickpea flour</a> (resembles scrambled eggs) at home all the time. Chickpea flour is a staple on Pino, and works very well for okonomiyaki.</p><p><b>Nagaimo:</b> If you're in a place were nagaimo (or yamaimo) is available, we highly reccommend adding it to the dish. It makes a fluffier pancake. Although we've made okonomiyaki without nagaimo before, so if you can't find it know that it will work and be very delicious anyway. It imparts little flavor, all it does is add nutrition and texture. Nagaimo, unlike most potatoes, can be eaten raw. However, it is best to handle the nagaimo with gloves, or to soak the peeled tuber in a vinegar-water solution to neutralize irritant <b>oxalate crystals</b> found on their skin. Nagaimo are low-calorie, high in protein, and have potassium, zinc, vitamin C and more. The texture of grated nagaimo can be off-putting, it looks like a regular tuber when whole, but when grated it becomes slime, almost liquid. This sort of texture is well-liked in Japan and referred to as being 'neba neba' (slimy). This texture present in many other foods like okra and nattou. This texture makes it an ideal egg alternative, it can be used to make deserts when baking.</p><p><b>Aonori:</b> Aonori is another obscure ingredient, but again, it can be omitted, although it tastes really amazing with it. We made okonomiyaki without it when we were in Majuro, because it simply wasn't available, so we used finely cut nori instead. Obviously, this isn't a perfect substitution, because aonori is sweet and tastes nothing like nori. However, nori is still very delicious and pairs well enough with the okonomiyaki.</p><p><b class='head'>Okonomi sauce</b></p><p>In this recipe, we don't use true 'okonomi sauce'. Why? Because we don't use many pre-made sauces, we prefer to make my own. Okonomi sauce requires many ingredients, and honestly, the sauce we've made works really well in this recipe and makes a good okonomi sauce alternative.</p><p>If you want to make your own, you can mix 7g (1 1/2 tsp) <a href='#whole_can_sugar.html'>sugar</a>, 45g (3 tbsp) <b>ketchup</b> and 45g (3 tbsp) of vegan <b>worcestershire sauce</b>. If you are like us, and don't care to buy pre-made sauces but want to avoid buying both ketchup and worcestershire sauce, you can make these too:</p><p><b>Worcestershire sauce:</b> combine <a href='apple_cider_vinegar.html'>apple cider vinegar</a>, water, <a href='soy_sauce.html'>soy sauce</a>, <a href='#natural_brown_sugar.html'>sugar</a>, <a href='#mustard_seeds.html'>mustard powder</a>, onion powder, garlic powder, <a href='cinnamon.html'>cinnamon</a> and <a href='black_pepper.html'>black pepper</a> in pan, bring to a boil and cook for a minute, then let cool.</p><p><b>Ketchup:</b> Using some <b>fresh tomato sauce</b> may be enough, otherwise add a bit of <a href='#natural_brown_sugar.html'>sugar</a> and <a href='apple_cider_vinegar.html'>apple cider vinegar</a> to it.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/okonomiyaki.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>pandanus fruit bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/pandanus_fruit_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>pandanus_fruit_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/pandanus_fruit_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We arrived in the <a href='https://100r.co/pages/the_promise_of_pancakes.html' target='_blank'>Marshall Islands 3 weeks ago</a>. We are settled in, but one thing remains difficult for us: finding fresh produce. The vegetables in Majuro are imported from either Guam, or Hawaii by cargo ship, and because they spend much time at sea they are frozen. Freezing fresh whole vegetables is never a good idea, the vegetables rot before they make it onto the shelves. When possible, we opt for local produce. Majuro has few native fresh vegetables, but they do have some fruit and among these is <b>the pandanus fruit</b>.</p><p>Pandanus, or <a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pandanus_tectorius' target='_blank'>Pandanus tectorius</a>, bears a fruit that look like a giant pinecone, it is made up of little wedge-like phalanges, commonly referred to as 'keys'. Each fruit has about 40-80 keys, the part of the keys that is attached to the core is soft, and a bright orange colour. In the Marshall Islands, people suck on the orange part which is sweet and tastes of cane sugar. The soft part can also be cut, and processed into juice. It is possible to make the juice yourself, this <b><a href='http://www.cuisinivity.com/globalfeast/pacific/Marshall_Islands/2012/Pandanus.php' target='_blank'>blog post</a></b> explains the process at length.</p><p>I don't have the space, nor the tools to prepare pandanus juice, but a store in Majuro sells frozen purée. This is what I used to prepare this pandanus fruit cake and the topping that goes with it. What does it taste like? It is similar to mango, sweet, but also bitter.</p><p>I bought a generous portion of frozen pandanus purée, and couldn't use most of it in the bread so we used the rest to make a topping. The chia seeds don't act as a thickener and can be omitted, but they add nutritional value to the meal.</p><p>If you ever come across some pandanus fruit, please try it! Making pandanus juice from scratch requires some muscle and serious dedication, but in places where it grows, chances are you'll also find a 'processed' version.</p><p>Pandanus Tectorius photo credit: U. S. Geological Survey, USGS /Forest & Kim Starr.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/pandanus_fruit_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>pan fried breadfruit</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/pan_fried_breadfruit.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>pan_fried_breadfruit</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/pan_fried_breadfruit.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Breadfruit trees are everywhere in French Polynesia, but sometimes the fruit aren’t mature enough to pick. To make things more difficult, grocery stores don’t sell them (they don’t sell fruit at all). The Polynesians don't buy fruit, they don't have to, they have plenty growing on their property. Getting our hands on a breadfruit was no simple task, on every island we would ask the locals, but again the fruit weren’t ready to pick off just yet.</p><p>We had breadfruit when we first arrived in Nuku Hiva, the owner of Snack Vaeki prepared some for us. The chef cooked it outside, over hot coals. The taste is hard to describe, it tastes like potato, but sweeter. We had the cooked breadfruit with some fresh coconut milk, extracted from a fresh coconut before our very eyes. Since then, we’ve been looking to cook it ourselves.</p><p>Then finally we got our chance! We bought a breadfruit at the Fare street market in Huahine. The seller at the fruit stand gave it a few knocks, and told us it was ready to eat! It was delicious with coconut milk, but we wanted to try something different. We cut the breadfruit into wedges and pan-fried it. We then served it with some button mushrooms, coated with sweetened soy sauce.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/pan_fried_breadfruit.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>papaya bruschetta topping</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/papaya_bruschetta_topping.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>papaya_bruschetta_topping</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/papaya_bruschetta_topping.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Before we arrived in the Marquesas, people made a point of telling us how difficult it was to find vegetables there. We heard that if we wanted tomatoes, we would need to get up at 0400 to get them at the market. We are early risers, but we lack the will to take the dinghy to shore in the dark. It's just as well, because others we met who had tried, came back empty-handed. In the Marquesas, most vegetables are brought in by supply ships, you can never be certain of what you're going to get. Potatoes, cucumbers, cabbages and eggplants we had plenty of, but vegetables like tomatoes, pumpkins, bok choy and salad greens were like rare pokemon.</p><p>We'd only ever made bruschetta topping with tomatoes, never thought of changing it for anything else. But then we thought, what looks like tomatoes? Papaya, sort of? They have a similar reddish tint, comparable texture too. Papaya is something Nuku Hiva has plenty of, and as it turns out, we prefer it over tomatoes now. Papaya is more firm and sweet, and pairs well with balsamic vinegar. We imagine it would taste great with mangoes too, it's something we may try when we get a craving again.</p><p>If something isn't available, or is too expensive where you are (hunting for raspberries in Japan comes to mind), swap it out for something else. Not every ingredient will work, but it's fun to try.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/papaya_bruschetta_topping.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>shepherds pie</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/shepherds_pie.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>shepherds_pie</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/shepherds_pie.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Shepherd's pie is one of our favorite childhood meals. It's a super versatile dish, our recipe has layers consisting of tofu and burmese tofu, green peas, sweet potato and cauliflower.</p><p>Shepherd's pie is very much like Pâté Chinois, everyone in Quebec refers to this dish as such, but because I suspect it has racist origins (no one is entirely sure where the name comes from) I'm going to refrain from using that term.</p><p>Families in Quebec make this all the time, but the traditional version includes meat and creamed corn. This recipe is different, but inspires the same kind of comfort.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions:</b></p><p>We've made versions of this dish with just cauliflower, or just using tofu, or just potatoes too. We've made it so often we've gone through every possibility. All in all, it consists of a <b>protein layer</b> (tofu, burmese tofu, lentils etc) <b>veggie layer</b> (corn or peas), and topped with a <b>root or hearty vegetable layer</b> (potatoes, pumpkin, parnisps, cauliflower etc).</p><p>I've also made a version which consists of cubed, cooked potatoes (or pumpkin), with scrambled chickpea flour and corn.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/shepherds_pie.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>quick sunflower seed parmesan</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_sunflower_seed_parmesan.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>quick_sunflower_seed_parmesan</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/quick_sunflower_seed_parmesan.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A simple recipe, for people with an allergy to tree nuts. Sunflower seeds come apart well, and like cashews or other nuts, create a pleasant texture and taste.</p><p>We made this parmesan to use over lasagna, it adds a bit of crunch to the top layer. It would also be delicious if sprinkled over pasta.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_sunflower_seed_parmesan.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>raisin beet bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/raisin_beet_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>raisin_beet_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/raisin_beet_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>If like Rekka's dad you like raisin bread, you will love this sweet raisin beet bread. It's halfway between a cake and bread. Adapted from an old cookbook by Margo Oliver <b>les menus de margo oliver</b>.</p><p>It's simple to make, and you can replace the raisins with currants or cranberries. If you make this recipe, just be sure to add plenty of raisins on top, we emptied a bag on it, without regret. They raisins get super crispy, and will develop a sweet crispy caramelized taste.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/raisin_beet_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>roasted carrots with beluga lentils</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_carrots_with_beluga_lentils.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>roasted_carrots_with_beluga_lentils</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/roasted_carrots_with_beluga_lentils.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Our oven has been working overtime these days, we've been baking and roasting food almost everyday. We picked up a pack of heirloom carrots at the market last weekend, threw them in the oven with a bit of oil, and served them over a bed of beluga lentils, topped it with a spicy peanut butter sauce.</p><p>Roasted carrots are sweet, a nice change from eating them raw.</p><p>Beluga lentils aren't the cheapest kind you can get, but we like them because they hold their shape well.</p><p><b>Credits:</b> The idea to make a recipe with beluga lentils was inspired by Meike Peters' <a href='https://eatinmykitchen.meikepeters.com/beluga-lentil-salad-with-pear-blue-cheese-and-thyme/' target='_blank'>beluga lentil salad recipe</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_carrots_with_beluga_lentils.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>roasted pumpkin seeds</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_pumpkin_seeds.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>roasted_pumpkin_seeds</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/roasted_pumpkin_seeds.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Our favorite way to eat pumpkin seeds, is to roast them with spices, it makes a nice snack or add-on to soups or other meals.</p><p>Roasted pumpkin seeds are delicious with almost anything, the sweet of the maple syrup with the spicy taste of the paprika is perfect, it is subtle, but very good.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/roasted_pumpkin_seeds.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>scrambled chickpea flour</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/scrambled_chickpea_flour.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>scrambled_chickpea_flour</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/scrambled_chickpea_flour.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>An ingredient that is important in our galley, is <a href='chickpea_flour.html'>chickpea flour</a>, also known as garbanzo flour, gram flour and besan flour. It is not an essential ingredient, but we really love it. It helps to give our meals variety, plus it has a long shelf life due to the low-moisture and low-fat content.</p><p>Chickpea flour has a texture and taste that is ideal for savoury pancakes or faux-omelettes. As this recipe suggests, it also makes a very good alternative to scrambled tofu.</p><p><b class='head'>Flavors</b></p><p>You can add extra flavorings, like chili pepper flakes, curry powder, cumin, smoked paprika or liquid smoke for an extra kick.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations:</b></p><p>I like to eat scrambled chickpea flour with a side of sliced avocado, topped with a drizzle of sambal oelek or <a href='sriracha.html'>sriracha</a>. Sometimes when we make meal salads, we add it for bulk. Another meal we enjoy with this recipe is a sort of ovenless deconstructed <a href='shepherds_pie.html'>shepherd's pie</a> (Quebec-style), we eat it with mashed potatoes, corn and sambal oelek.</p><p>You can also make this with cooked chickpeas by smashing them with a fork and mixing them up with nutritional yeast, salt and other flavorings.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/scrambled_chickpea_flour.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>spicy brownies with pomegranate syrup</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/spicy_brownies_with_pomegranate_syrup.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>spicy_brownies_with_pomegranate_syrup</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/spicy_brownies_with_pomegranate_syrup.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A brownie recipe with a kick, topped with a chili-infused pomegranate syrup.</p><p>We put a LOT of chili pepper flakes in these. You can omit the chilis in the batter, but we recommend keeping it in the pomegranate syrup. It's delicious and won't be the same without it.</p><p>You can vary the fruit juice for the topping. Making reductions of fruit juices is very easy, it adds a 'touch of fancy'.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p><b>Fat :</b> Use 60 g (~1/4 cup) vegan butter instead of oil. If you do this, you'll have to heat the cocoa powder, butter, salt, sugar and spices in a double boiler or any small pan placed over a pot of gently simmering water. When you mix the chocolate/butter mix with the flour, beat vigorously (40-50 strokes) with a spatula so that the fat doesn't separate when baking. Alternatively, you can use coconut oil, but it will alter the base flavor of the brownies in a big way. It's better to use neutral oils, like sunflower. A final option is to use 100% vegan butter, if you want to do this add 145 g (~10 tbsp) to your recipe instead of the canola oil and pumpkin.</p><p>Final tip: To prevent burning the bottom of your brownies, place the pan on a preheated cookie sheet. Brownie tips courtesy of <a href='http://www.kitchenproject.com/history/Brownies/BrownieTips.htm#Mixing'>the kitchen project</a>.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/spicy_brownies_with_pomegranate_syrup.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>stovetop blackberry cake</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_blackberry_cake.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>stovetop_blackberry_cake</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/stovetop_blackberry_cake.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>In British Columbia, we like to walk around to pick blackberries in the summer. There are blackberry bushes everywhere. We brought a bowl with us, and filled it up in one short hour! We made a cake with the berries that same night.</p><p><b>Substitutions:</b></p><p><b>Milk:</b> Oat milk works well as a substitute.<br><b>Flour:</b> You're welcome to use all purpose flour, or a mixture cut with spelt. We used 100% whole wheat because we're trying to get used to carrying one type of flour. The cake rose well.</br><b>Oil:</b> Can substitute for any other neutral oil, like sunflower and grapeseed. The fat in this recipe was already reduced, I don't recommend using less.<br><b>Fruit:</b> This recipe works well with other berries, or fruit like banana, apples etc.</p><p><b>Haybox:</b></p><p>A haybox is a cooker that utilizes the heat of the food being cooked to complete the cooking process. Food items to be cooked are heated to boiling point, and then insulated.</p><p>After pan off the stove, we transfer it to a bin with clothing. We layer a dish cloth underneath and overtop, and then bury it with clothes, or a sleeping bag. The cast iron retains its heat well, and the layers of fabric help to retain it even further. It's a way to save fuel when cooking. We also like to use our pressure cooker to retain heat, but we can only ever do that when we use our cast iron pot (it fits inside, the pan doesn't). <b>NOTE: Although, a half recipe works better than full, because it is more difficult to heat a thicker cake all the way through</b>. As soon as we take it off the heat, we put it in the pressure cooker, add the lid and plug up the top. It stayed warm for an entire hour. In winter, these systems may not retain the heat as well, more insulation may be necessary.</p><p><b>If you prefer to bake this cake in the oven</b>, see the instructions at the bottom of the recipe.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_blackberry_cake.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>stovetop choco oat cookies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_choco_oat_cookies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>stovetop_choco_oat_cookies</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/stovetop_choco_oat_cookies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>These days, I've been experimenting with baking without an oven. This limits what recipes we can make, but also gives us plenty of opportunities for learning how to do things differently.</p><p>We prepared the 'dough' on the stovetop, using a cast-iron pan. Any kind of pan will do, we just really like cast iron. The resulting texture is very moist compared to a traditional cookie, but it is very delicious and requires few tools to prepare.</p><p><b class='head'>Recipe notes:</b></p><p><b>Oats:</b> Only use quick-cooking oats, as <a href='rolled_oats.html'>rolled oats</a> or steel-cut oats will not absorb moisture as quickly, and the 'dough' won't bind. Making your own quick-oats is easy, just pop some rolled oats in a blender, or pulverize with a mortar and pestle. Don't overblend, as you'll end up with oat powder.</p><p><b>Vegan butter:</b> Vegan butter adds flavor. It's possible to substitute with coconut oil, but it will alter the flavor. To make your own vegan butter, look for the recipe in The Homemade Vegan Pantry by Miyoko Schinner. It's possible to omit the butter entirely and to double the quantity of peanut butter.</p><p><b>Cocoa powder:</b> If you have a sensitivity to caffeine use <a href='carob.html'>carob powder</a> instead. Switching to carob will alter the flavor of the cookie — in a good way.</p><p><b>Sugar:</b> You can substitute with any other kind of sugar, but if you choose to add commercial brown sugar reduce the added water content (a little).</p><p><b>Soy milk:</b> We make this recipe with just water often, but adding soy milk (or any other nut milk) makes for a richer flavor.</p><p><b>Peanut butter:</b> We like peanut butter a lot, so we add it in everything. We use 100% peanut butter. If you use a sweetened variety, you can use less sugar.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_choco_oat_cookies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>cheesy sunflower seed sauce</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/cheesy_sunflower_seed_sauce.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>cheesy_sunflower_seed_sauce</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/cheesy_sunflower_seed_sauce.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Rekka is allergic to tree nuts, but this doesn't mean that our choices of 'vegan cheeses' are limited. Seeds and treenuts are interchangeable in many recipes and produce similar results, while being just as creamy and just as nutritious.</p><p>To soften the seeds, it's possible to quick-boil them. This makes it easier to grind down into a sauce. If you've got the time, soaking them for 1-2h is a better option (<a href='https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4325021/' target='_blank'>ref</a>).</p><p><a href='sprouting.html#otherseeds'>Sprouting sunflower seeds</a> is another good nutritious option, but I haven't had much luck sprouting mine.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/cheesy_sunflower_seed_sauce.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sourdough spelt flatbread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/sourdough_spelt_flatbread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>sourdough_spelt_flatbread</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/sourdough_spelt_flatbread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Sourdough flatbreads are the more complex version of my <a href='quick_flat_bread.html'>quick flat bread</a> recipe. The added complexity is a small price to pay for a delicious, sour pita.</p><p>I like to use 100% spelt flour, but for a better rise add up to 2 cups of all purpose and 1 cup of spelt flour (note: my starter is also 100% spelt). Spelt has more gluten than some other ancient grains, like <a href='einkorn_wheat_flour.html'>einkorn</a>. It's also higher in protein than <a href='whole_wheat_flour.html'>whole wheat flour</a>, and has a pleasant, nutty flavor. Substitute spelt 1:1 with whole wheat flour.</p><p><b class='head'>Sourdough starter</b></p><p>I've already written detailed instructions on how to make a sourdough starter, read about the process <a href='sourdough_starter.html'>here</a>. The starter used in this recipe is 100% hydration, which means it is equal parts of water to flour by weight.</p><p><b class='head'>Changing flour ratios:</b></p><p>If you want to change the quantity of flour, to make more or fewer flatbreads, use the 3-2-1 (flour-water-starter) plan to measure out the amount of water and starter:</p><p>3 parts flour: 2 parts water: 1 part starter at 100% hydration.</p><p>For example, say I'm starting with 450g of flour, then I'll need...<br />450 / 1.5 = 300 g water<br />450 / 3 = 150 g starter</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/sourdough_spelt_flatbread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sweet mock eel nigiri</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/sweet_mock_eel_nigiri.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>sweet_mock_eel_nigiri</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/sweet_mock_eel_nigiri.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Burmese tofu is not really tofu—we know it's confusing. Burmese tofu is made with chickpea flour, one of our staple foods. It takes 10 minutes to make and sets under 1 hour. It's a great soy-free alternative, and the texture is comparable to that of soft tofu.</p><p>The original recipe for chickpea tofu was sourced from a book called The Burmese Kitchen by Aung Thein. This recipe will use up about half of the burmese tofu, which means you'll have a whole other half to use in other meals.</p><p>We thought the chickpea tofu would be well-suited as a 'mock unagi kabayaki', and that it would look especially striking atop some black rice.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/sweet_mock_eel_nigiri_2.jpg'/></p><p>The sauce served over unagi (eel) kabayaki is sweet, with hints of caramel. Most Japanese sauces are easy to make, and usually require around 3-4 ingredients, these almost always include: soy sauce, sake, mirin, or Japanese rice vinegar. If you want to cook Japanese food, having these around is a must.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/sweet_mock_eel_nigiri.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>tzatziki</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/tzatziki.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>tzatziki</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/tzatziki.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Making tzatziki is easy. This is a basic recipe that works well enough with all kinds of substitutions, depending on dietary restrictions.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>It is possible to use <a href='sunflower_seeds.html'>sunflower seeds</a> and <a href='tofu.html'>tofu</a> to replace the hemp seeds. In this recipe, we used half hemp and half soy, because hemp, while being nutritious, is not cheap. Using just <a href='shelled_hemp_seeds.html'>shelled hemp seeds</a> is very possible.</p><p>If using sunflower seeds, it is better to pre-soak them for 1-2h prior to blending. If using only tofu, you may not require extra water in the recipe.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/tzatziki.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>seitan</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/seitan.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>seitan</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/seitan.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p><b>Seitan</b> (say-tan) or <b>wheat meat</b>, is very meat-like, it's prepared using a variation of spices and other seasonings. It is the base of Buddhist vegetarian cooking, and has been documented in China since the 6th century. It's an ingredient that is also present in Japanese cuisine, for <b>Shojin Ryori</b> (vegetarian cooking)—an important term to remember if you don't eat meat and are traveling there. Seitan takes on a different name there, it is known as <b>Fu</b>, and can be found in two forms: raw (nama-fu) or dry-baked (yaki-fu, which looks like bread).</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/seitan_2.jpg'/></p><p>Seitan, or Fu, can be produced at home, but it's very labor intensive. Making it requires kneading wheat flour with water to rinse out the starch from the wheat, what remains is a sticky mass of pure gluten protein. If your plan is to make it from scratch, good on you, but otherwise, <a href='gluten_flour.html'>gluten flour</a> (or vital wheat gluten) is your best bet. The basic ingredients for seitan are gluten flour and water, but it's best to flavor it with other ingredients as it is rather bland on its own. The amount of liquid that you use to make your dough will also affect the chewiness of your seitan, less waters means more chewy with a harder texture, and more will make it tender.</p><p>In this recipe, we added chickpea flour for added nutrition. Wheat gluten proteins are deficient in lysine (an essential amino acid for good health), adding a lysine-rich food like chickpea flour to the mix makes up for this deficiency.</p><p>When preparing seitan, it's important to flavor both the inside and outside of the dough. Adding a variation of ingredients to the dough mix such as <a href='ginger.html'>ginger</a>, <a href='garlic.html'>garlic</a>, <a href='onion_powder.html'>onion powder</a>, <a href='tomato_sauce.html'>tomato sauce</a>, <a href='soy_sauce.html'>soy sauce</a> and so on will make it extra flavorful, the same goes for the broth. Adding vegetable broth and <a href='soy_sauce.html'>soy sauce</a> as a base, and roughly chopped <a href='onions.html'>onions</a>, <a href='garlic.html'>garlic</a> and <a href='ginger.html'>ginger</a> will season the outside of the dough.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/seitan_4.jpg'/></p><p>There are <b>3 ways</b> to cook seitan: <b>boiling, steaming or baking</b>. In this recipe, we used the boiling method. Steaming requires wrapping the dough in foil or some other wrapper to help it keep its shape, then steaming it in a steamer basket over a pot of boiling water for 30 minutes or so. Baking the seitan, means flattening or stretching the dough to fit the baking dish, adding seasonings overtop, and baking it for an hour. All methods are good, but some are better for certain kinds of meals.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/seitan.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>shichimi togarashi crackers</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/shichimi_togarashi_crackers.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>shichimi_togarashi_crackers</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/shichimi_togarashi_crackers.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>We like making our own crackers, and to play around with different flavors. We enjoy the taste of the Japanese spice mix <b>Shichimi Togarashi</b>, which translates to '7-flavor chili pepper'.</p><p><b>How to make your own spice mix:</b></p><p>If you have a well-stocked spice rack, you can easily make it yourself. Mix together: 30 g chili flakes, 15 g sanshou (sichuan peppercorns), 15 g <a href='dried_orange_peel.html'>dried orange peel</a>, 5 g <a href='black_sesame_seeds.html'>black sesame seeds</a>, 5 g <a href='white_sesame_seeds.html'>white sesame seeds</a>, 10 g ground ginger and 10 g <a href='aonori.html'>aonori</a>.</p><p>Some people substitute sichuan peppercorns for black peppercorns, we don't reccommend doing that, as they're not interchangeable, sichuan peppercorns are what makes it taste awesome. It's a numbing pepper, with a really distinctive taste and aroma. If you eat one peppercorn, you'll notice right away that it numbs your tongue and alters your sense of taste.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/shichimi_togarashi_crackers.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>spicy stirfry chickpeas</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/spicy_stirfry_chickpeas.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>spicy_stirfry_chickpeas</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/spicy_stirfry_chickpeas.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>If someone was to ask us which food we could eat forever without stopping, we'd answer chickpeas. There's a TON of different ways to prepare them, and all of these ways are delicious. Chickpeas are delicious when baked, squished, pureed, ground and sprouted. Their versatility make our lives easier, we can eat them everyday and it doesn't ever get boring.</p><p><b>Nutrition</b>: Legumes is an important part of the diet, and one of the best plant sources of <b>lysine</b>, one of 9 essential amino acids required for good health. Protein is necessary for muscles, bones, hormones, digestive enzymes, to absorb nutrients and to rebuild cells. If you eat 1/2 cup dry beans a day, your daily protein needs are covered.</p><p>Another plus is that dry chickpeas keep a long, long time. If you keep them in air-tight containers they will last even longer, because moisture and oxygen is the enemy of all beans. Oxygen makes the bean oils rancid overtime. You can store them for 5+ yrs if you add oxygen absorbers (packet consisting of powdered iron oxide) to the containers. We like to buy them in bulk and cook them as needed. An advantage of buying them dry is that it is cheap, and they taste better (honest). Read about <a href='https://extension.usu.edu/foodstorage/howdoi/dry_beans' target='_blank'>storing dry beans</a>.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations:</b></p><p>Adding a <a href='bay_leaf.html'>bay leaf</a>, a bit of <a href='onion.html'>onion</a> or a clove or two of <a href='garlic.html'>garlic</a> to the cooking water add a subtle seasoning to the <a href='chickpeas.html'>chickpeas</a> and boost flavor.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/spicy_stirfry_chickpeas.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>spinach oatmeal cookies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/spinach_oatmeal_cookies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>spinach_oatmeal_cookies</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/spinach_oatmeal_cookies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>When making green cookies, spinach is an obvious choice, it adds colour, nutrition, and doesn't alter the flavor of the food.</p><p>This recipe also doesn't take very long to make and does not require flour. It makes 5 small cookies, it's easy and doesn't make a mess. We never bake huge batches of desserts, but if you want more you can double or triple the recipe.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/spinach_oatmeal_cookies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>stovetop popcorn</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_popcorn.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>stovetop_popcorn</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/stovetop_popcorn.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Making popcorn on the stovetop is not a recipe perse, it's a reminder that it's easy to do and that it doesn't require any specialized tools or ingredients. It doesn't require a microwave, just a pot and source of heat (stove).</p><p>When Rekka was a kid their family used Jiffy Pop, unpopped kernels, oil, and flavoring agents that come in a heavy-gauge aluminum foil pan. Rekka enjoyed seeing the foil rise up into a dome as the kernels started to pop. Then later, their family adopted microwavable bags. These products—while easy and fun—cost more and create unecessary waste. Because we grew up with packaged popcorn, the idea of trying to pop our own kernels only occurred to us MUCH later in life.</p><p>So, again, this is a reminder that there are conveniences in life that we just don't need.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/stovetop_popcorn.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sweet and sour lentils</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/sweet_and_sour_lentils.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>sweet_and_sour_lentils</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/sweet_and_sour_lentils.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>In our galley we have a few recipes that we consider staples, that we're always in the mood to eat. We usually rotate these throughout the week, adding maybe a new recipe or two to change things up. This sweet and sour lentils recipe is one of our favorites.</p><p>You can eat the lentils as is, or scoop it up with crackers. We enjoy eating it wrapped in salad or cabbage leaves.</p><p>We've cooked sweet and sour lentils often on long passages, it's a simple one-pot meal. It's also our go-to recipe during pot lucks—even people who don't like lentils will enjoy it (we've never had any complaints).</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>It's a versatile recipe, so if we don't have any carrots or daikon we'll sometimes put brocoli or fresh green peas instead. For a heartier meal, adding sweet potatoes is also delicious. Sometimes, if we're out of peanut butter, we'll use sesame paste instead, the flavor is very similar and doesn't change much in the recipe (also nice for those with peanut allergies). This recipe only works with whole lentils, because there's still a bite to them, halved lentils will soften too much and the resulting texture won't be as pleasant.</p><p>Enjoy this humble, but delicious recipe.</p><p><b class='head'>Sprouted lentils</b></p><p>If you use sprouted lentils, the cooking time is reduced by more than half. It can help you save on both time, and fuel, while making the lentils more digestible. For sprouting techniques, refer to <a href='sprouting.html#garbanzo'>lentils</a> in the sprouting guide.</p><p>The directions for the recipes will differ a bit. For this version of the recipe, cut the vegetables real small (tiny cubes) so they cook fast, then brown them in a pan with oil. When the veggies are done, add the sprouted lentils, and cook the mixture for 2-3 min. Finally, add the sauce, mixing well and cooking the mixture for another minute or so to allow the sauce to thicken. Top with some chives.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/sweet_and_sour_lentils.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>uzumaki hummus bites</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/uzumaki_hummus_bites.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>uzumaki_hummus_bites</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/uzumaki_hummus_bites.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p><b>Uzumaki</b> means 'spiral' in Japanese, it is also the name of Rekka's favorite Junji Ito story. We thought this to be a good name for these savoury beet hummus bites.</p><p>Making tortillas at home is overall easy, but making perfect circles is a challenge and comes with practice. A tortilla press is only ever necessary if you care about the shape. I've gotten good results with a simple rolling pin.</p><p>Making the tortillas black is optional, but it adds a nice contrast to the beet hummus.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/uzumaki_hummus_bites.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>vegemite caramel</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/vegemite_caramel.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>vegemite_caramel</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/vegemite_caramel.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Vegemite is very salty, and we thought it would pair well with something sweet.</p><p>We used deglet noor dates for this recipe, but feel free to use medjool dates instead. Medjool dates are great, but expensive, and their cheaper counterpart works just fine. The added soy milk helps cut the salty/sweet of the mixture.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/vegemite_caramel.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>vege pate</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/vege_pate.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>vege_pate</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/vege_pate.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Végé pâté is Quebec staple food. It's great with veggies, on crackers and in sandwiches. My recipe is grainy because of the use of rolled oats, but don't worry, it still holds itself well together.</p><p>Purchasing it pre-made can be expensive, and not all brands are good. Making your own is no trouble, and if frozen, it can keep for a long, long time.</p><p><b class='head'>Substitutions</b></p><p>A lot of végé pâté recipes call for whole wheat flour, we've made pâté with it before with great results. Using flour will result in a smoother pâté. If you don't have oats, you can use whole wheat flour, or other wholegrain flours instead.</p><p>It's also possible to use regular potatoes, or pumpkin instead of sweet potatoes.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/vege_pate.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>wakame bites</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/wakame_bites.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>wakame_bites</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/wakame_bites.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Seaweed bites, a great snack packed with a good dose of iodine, necessary for good health.</p><p>We used our fancy cookie cutters, but most times we just cut the sheets of dough into small squares with a regular knife. Using cookie cutters is longer, because we want to use every bit of the dough and that means re-using the bits around the cut-outs.</p><p>The cookies were adapted from a recipe by <a href='http://www.food-sommelier.jp/recipe/R0123/173155.html' target='_blank'>Kiuchi Yuki-san</a></p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/wakame_bites.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>wasabi swirl chocolate cookies</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/wasabi_swirl_chocolate_cookies.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>wasabi_swirl_chocolate_cookies</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/wasabi_swirl_chocolate_cookies.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Black sesame chocolate cookies with a wasabi glaze, it's surprising how well these two things go together.</p><p>we wanted to mix the wasabi directly in the cookies at first, but after reading a lot about baking wasabi, we decided to apply it after in the form of a glaze because the taste of wasabi fades significantly when heated.</p><p>It doesn't taste too strong, and adds just the right amount of kick.</p><p><b class='head'>Quick Yogurt</b></p><p>To make quick yogurt or sour milk, add apple cider vinegar to soy milk. The vinegar makes soy curdle and thicken, and adds sourness that makes it taste more complex.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/wasabi_swirl_chocolate_cookies.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>golden bread</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/golden_bread.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>golden_bread</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/golden_bread.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>In Quebec we call french toast 'pain doré', which translates to 'golden bread'. A fitting name. Pain doré is best made with older, and softer bread. Rekka's family recipe differs in the way that it requires dairy and eggs. Substituting eggs in recipes is never easy, but not impossible. We've tried many alternatives over the years and finally ended up using chickpea flour. It's an ingredient we already use in many recipes to mimic eggs, like in <a href='okonomiyaki.html'>okonomiyaki</a> and <a href='scrambled_chickpea_flour.html'>scrambled chickpea flour</a>. When heated, chickpea flour thickens and crisps up while keeping its yellow color. We don't recommend using bananas as an egg replacer in this recipe. It's what we used to do, but it imparts too much flavor and makes it too sweet.</p><p><b>Oven version :</b> Preheat oven at 180°C. Grease a baking dish, add sliced bread and pour the left-over milk mixture overtop. Cook until golden.</p><p><b>Bread :</b> In this recipe I used some spelt sandwich bread.</p><p><b>Milk : </b> Adding vinegar to plant milk makes it curdle and taste sour, it's a simple trick used to make dairy-free buttermilk. In recipes, buttermilk adds sharpness and flavor. You're welcome to use other types of plant milk, but some varieties (like rice milk) won't curdle as well.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/golden_bread.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sourdough starter</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/sourdough_starter.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>sourdough_starter</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/sourdough_starter.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>Sourdough bread has been arounds for a long time. People are still making it today, even with the existence of baker's yeast.</p><p>The fermentation required to prepare it improves the flavor of the dough, and makes it easier for the body to absorb the <a href='nutrition.html#zinc'>dietary minerals</a> present in the grains.</p><p>Making sourdough bread begins with a sourdough starter. The starter is a fermenting mixture of flour and water containing microorganisms which include wild yeast and lactobacilli. The yeast produces carbon dioxide which leavens the dough, and the lactobacilli produce lactic acid which contribute flavor. The process is simple, it requires more waiting than active cooking time. We've made a summary of common questions and concerns when it comes to making a starter.</p><p><b><a id='discard'>WHY DISCARD?</a></b></p><p>Discarding starter is necessary as it quickly builds up in a jar and becomes difficult to manage. The discard works well in a variety of baked goods.</p><p><b>ADAPTING YEAST RECIPES</b></p><p>There are some key aspects to converting yeast recipes to sourdough, like hydration level and yeast. <a href='https://www.culturesforhealth.com/learn/sourdough/hydration-sourdough-starter/' target='_blank'>Hydration level</a> is the ratio of water to flour in a starter. You can maintain or adjust the hydration level with each feeding based on the ratio of water to flour you feed your starter. Aiming for 100% hydration, or equal weights of flour and water, is recommended.</p><p>To calculate how much added yeast is necessary, first you have to know that the rising power of 7 g of yeast (1 packet) is roughly equivalent to 226 g (1 cup) of sourdough starter.</p><p>With this information it's easy to approximate the amount of added water, flour and yeast in a recipe.</p><p><b>FEEDINGS</b></p><p>The starter needs feedings at <b>12 h intervals daily</b> in the first week, and <b>once a day afterwards</b>. As long as this starter culture is fed flour and water regularly it will remain active.</p><p><b>I forgot to feed my starter!</b> Forgetting to feed the starter isn't a big deal, feed it as soon as you remember. Feedings of longer than three days acidify the dough and may change the microbial ecosystem.<br /><b>Did i feed my starter too much?</b> Feeding the wrong amount won't kill it, but it may make it appear too dry or too wet and may not rise as expected. You can correct the feeding by adding either more flour or water, it will right itself.<br /><b>What's the liquid on top of my starter?</b> This liquid is the alcohol given off as the wild yeast ferments. This doesn't mean it's going bad, it indicates that your starter is hungry.</p><p><b>FLOUR</b></p><p>Using wholemeal instead of processed flour for your starter is a good idea because it provides a variety of organisms and minerals.</p><p><b>FILTERED WATER</b></p><p>Using filtered (carbon filter) or distilled water instead of plain tap ensures good fermentation, as sourdough relies on microorganisms that chlorine inhibits. Leaving tap water uncovered for 24 h will allow the chlorine to dissipate.</p><p><b>Can my starter go bad?</b> Starters require more attention on the initial 6-10 days it takes to create a healthy mature starter. It hasn't yet developed defenses that characterize a mature starter. Mature starter cultures are stable because of their pH level and the presence of antibacterial agents, this helps prevent colonization by unwanted yeasts and bacteria. Sourdough breads keep fresh longer than regular bread for this reason too. The ideal temperature for starters is 21 °C, but a bit higher and lower won't hurt it. Yeast dies at 60 °C. If you see an pink or orange streak on your starter, this is a sure sign it's gone bad, discard and start over.</p><p>Good luck with your starter, and be sure to give it a name! Ours is called Teki, after a tern in Miyazaki's Future Boy Conan.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/sourdough_starter.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>soybean hummus with jalapenos</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/soybean_hummus_with_jalapenos.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>soybean_hummus_with_jalapenos</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/soybean_hummus_with_jalapenos.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>While in Japan, we didn't have access to chickpeas and so we started to make hummus with soybeans. The result is amazing, and both of us now prefer this version. Soybeans have a rich, creamy texture, and a neutral flavor.</p><p><b class='head'>Recommendations:</b></p><p><b>Acid:</b> We sometimes add lime, or apple cider vinegar if we don't have access to lemon. Doing this doesn't alter the flavor.</p><p><b>Soybeans</b>: It is possible to make hummus with any bean, but the taste and texture will differ. We have a preference for chickpeas and red lentils. If using chickpeas, if you want a very smooth hummus take the skins off prior to blending.</p><p><b>Miso:</b> We used a miso (米こうじみそ) that is characterized by the mellow sweetness of the rice. Using a darker variety would overwhelm the dish. If sensitive to soy, try and find chickpea miso.</p><p><b>Toppings:</b> Jalapeno peppers add kick, it makes this dish rather spicy and can be omitted. If you're not a fan of spicy, try adding roasted red peppers instead.</p><p><b>Garlic:</b> We like to put raw nira (Japanese garlic chives) as a topping, or instead of garlic. Nira is very mild, and pairs well with soybeans.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/soybean_hummus_with_jalapenos.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>bean chili</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/bean_chili.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>bean_chili</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/bean_chili.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>A hearty, warm dish. The above photo is the day-after portion.</p><p>When making chili, we swap vegetables in and out depending on what we have. For instance, we might add only carrots, or two parsnips, or potatoes. Parnips, like carrots, are cheap and plentiful in winter. Celery is common in chili recipes, but we omit it because Devine isn't a fan.<p><p><b>Beans</b>. For beans, we try and use black beans as the bulk of the recipe, but we like to add chickpeas. Chickpeas in chili is not common, but it's a legume that we always have on hand and that we both love (we don't keep pinto, or kidney beans). Swapping chickpeas for lentils would also be delicious.</p><p><b>Canned beans?</b> It is possible to use canned beans, but buying dry beans is cheaper, and means less weight on the boat. For those who insist on using cans, <b>1 drained 425 g (15 oz) can of chickpeas</b> and <b>1 drained 425 g (15 oz) cans of black beans</b> is fine for this recipe.</p><p><b>Beer?</b> Beer provides a great flavorful medium for the beans and vegetables to simmer in, it adds depth of flavor. Dark, stouts and amber beer lend well to chili. You can omit the broth or beer and exchange for <b>350 ml</b> of extra tomatoes and their juices.</p><p><b>Chile powder</b>. This is different than chili powder. Chile powder refers to pure dried, crushed (and sometimes smoked) chipotle, habanero, ancho, guajillo, piri piri, kashmiri, etc. There are no other added ingredients. To make your own, see <a href='chile_powder.html'>this recipe</a>.</p><p><b>Cocoa powder</b>. Adding cocoa powder is a trick we learned from making Japanese curry roux. Japanese cooks like to add chocolate. It pairs well with chili. Like beer, it adds depth to the dish.</a>.</p><p><b>Pressure cooker</b>. We use our pressure cooker to prepare our chili because it helps us save on fuel (our boat uses LPG), and because we prepare beans from dry. Adjust cooking times for your altitude.</p><p><b>Fresh tomatoes</b>. If you have plenty of chopped fresh tomatoes available, or if you can your own, you can use <b>800 g</b> (roughly 10 to 12 whole, although it depends on the kind of tomato, e.g., cherry vs roma) of chopped fresh tomatoes instead of a can.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/bean_chili.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
  <title>quick grilled cheese</title>
  <link>https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_grilled_cheese.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink='false'>quick_grilled_cheese</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0900</pubDate>
  <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rekka Bellum]]></dc:creator>
  <description>
<![CDATA[<img src='https://grimgrains.com/media/recipes/quick_grilled_cheese.jpg' width='600'/>
<div><p>There are now many good vegan cheese options to choose from, varying in complexity and cost, but we like to prepare a simple 'cheese-like' mixture when making a grilled-cheese. It takes less than 5 minutes to mix all the ingredients together, requiring no special tools.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/quick_grilled_cheese_3.jpg'/></p><p>The result is a thick, spreadable, and cheese-like mixture.</p><p><b>Substitutions</b></p><p><b>Plant milk</b>: If you don't like soy milk, any non-dairy milk will do. We'd recommend non-sweetened varieties or the taste may come through too much.</p><p><b>Miso</b>: We always have miso on the boat, and we use whatever kind we happen to have. We've made the mixture with white and red miso. The red miso has a stronger, deeper taste.</p><p><b>Nutritional yeast</b>: It is possible to omit the nutritional yeast, the 'cheese' will taste fine without it because of the presence of the miso, tahini and dijon mustard. If this ingredient is omitted, add less liquid so that the mixture remains thick.</p><p><img src='../media/recipes/quick_grilled_cheese_2.jpg'/></p><p><b>Olive oil</b>: We use olive oil to toast the sandwhiches in a pan, but it is possible to use vegan butter, and to pre-butter the bread prior to putting it in the pan. It is possible to dry-toast the sandwhiches in pan without added oil or vegan butter, but it may take longer to brown.</p></div><p><a href='https://grimgrains.com/site/quick_grilled_cheese.html'>Continue reading</a></p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
</channel></rss>